<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Copyright 2026 Ron Craig (rclinux) -->
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>io.github.rclinux.MintMechanic</id>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0-or-later</project_license>

  <name>Mint Mechanic</name>
  <summary>The maintained tune-up tool for Linux Mint</summary>

  <developer id="io.github.rclinux">
    <name>Ron Craig</name>
  </developer>

  <description>
    <p>
      Mint Mechanic is a modern, Cinnamon-native successor to Stacer: a live
      system dashboard with animated CPU, RAM and disk gauges plus a GPU dial,
      married to the maintenance actions Linux Mint does not ship.
    </p>
    <p>
      It deliberately stays out of the system-information lane that Mint already
      covers, and works in the action and optimization space instead.
    </p>
    <p>Features:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Dashboard with live analog gauges for CPU, RAM, disk and GPU, plus network throughput, load average and uptime</li>
      <li>Services — enable or disable systemd services with live status</li>
      <li>Startup — manage your per-user autostart entries</li>
      <li>Cleaner — reclaim space from the APT cache, orphaned packages, thumbnails, Trash and old system logs</li>
      <li>Uninstaller — search your manually-installed packages and remove them</li>
      <li>Streamline — export your installed package set as a portable profile, or import one to see what is missing</li>
      <li>A persistent GO/NO-GO health strip covering disk, failed units, pending updates and reboot-required</li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      Mint Mechanic never runs as root. Reads happen as your own user, and each
      individual action that changes the system elevates on its own through
      polkit. Anything that removes packages shows you what APT would actually
      remove — including everything pulled in through dependencies — and asks
      you to confirm, refusing outright if the removal would take your desktop,
      login manager or graphics driver with it.
    </p>
  </description>

  <launchable type="desktop-id">mint-mechanic.desktop</launchable>

  <url type="homepage">https://github.com/rclinux/mint-mechanic</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/rclinux/mint-mechanic/issues</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/rclinux/mint-mechanic</url>

  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <caption>The dashboard, with live CPU, RAM, disk and GPU gauges</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/rclinux/mint-mechanic/main/images/dashboard.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Enabling and disabling system services</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/rclinux/mint-mechanic/main/images/services.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Reclaiming disk space with the cleaner</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/rclinux/mint-mechanic/main/images/cleaner.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Exporting a portable package profile with Streamline</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/rclinux/mint-mechanic/main/images/streamline.png</image>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>

  <categories>
    <category>System</category>
    <category>Settings</category>
  </categories>

  <keywords>
    <keyword>tweak</keyword>
    <keyword>services</keyword>
    <keyword>cleaner</keyword>
    <keyword>dashboard</keyword>
    <keyword>gauges</keyword>
    <keyword>packages</keyword>
    <keyword>stacer</keyword>
    <keyword>maintenance</keyword>
  </keywords>

  <provides>
    <binary>mint-mechanic</binary>
  </provides>

  <content_rating type="oars-1.1"/>

  <releases>
    <release version="0.5.0" date="2026-07-19">
      <description>
        <p>
          Published to a PPA so updates arrive through the normal system update
          process, and added AppStream metadata so the app lists in software
          centres. Packaging moved to a standard Debian source package.
        </p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.0" date="2026-07-19">
      <description>
        <p>
          Adds a removal preview and confirmation to the Uninstaller, and moves
          the shared removal guard into the single package seam so the Cleaner
          and Uninstaller cannot diverge.
        </p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.0" date="2026-07-19">
      <description>
        <p>
          Safety fix: the Cleaner's orphaned-package task now shows APT's real
          removal cascade, requires confirmation, and refuses removals that
          would take session-critical packages.
        </p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.2.0" date="2026-07-19">
      <description>
        <p>
          Security fix for package-name handling when importing a Streamline
          profile, corrected path quoting in the Cleaner, and the addition of a
          test suite and continuous integration.
        </p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.0" date="2026-07-01">
      <description>
        <p>First release.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
</component>
